I have the feeling that we can all agree
أشعر أننا نتفق جميعًا
that we're moving towards a new
أننا نتجه نحو شكل جديد
model of the state and society.
للدولة والمجتمع
But, we're absolutely clueless as to what this is
لكننا نجهل تمامًا ماهية هذا الشكل
or what it should be.
أو كيف يجب أن يكون
It seems like we need to have
يبدو أننا بحاجة لمناقشة
a conversation about democracy
الديمقراطية
in our day and age.
في يومنا وعصرنا هذا
Let's think about it this way:
دعونا نقارب الموضوع كالتالي:
We are 21st-century citizens, doing our
نحن مواطنو القرن الواحد والعشرين
very, very best to interact with 19th century-designed institutions
نفعل ما بوسعنا للتفاعل مع مؤسسات القرن التاسع عشر
that are based on an information technology of the 15th century.
المبنية على تكنولوجيا المعلومات من القرن الخامس عشر
Let's have a look at some of the
لنلقي نظرة على بعض ميزات
characteristics of this system.
هذا النظام
First of all, it's designed for an information technology
أولًا، تم تصميمه من أجل تكنولوجيا المعلومات
that's over 500 years old.
التي تعود لأكثر من 500 سنة
And the best possible system
وأفضل نظام يمكن تصميمه
that could be designed for it
من أجل هذا الغرض
is one where the few make daily decisions
هو نظام حيث يصنع بضعة أشخاص قراراتهم اليومية
in the name of the many.
باسم الكثير من الناس
And the many get to vote once every couple of years.
ويصوت هؤلاء الناس كل بضعة سنوات
In the second place, the costs of
ثانيًا، كلفة المشاركة
participating in this system are
في هذا النظام
incredibly high.
باهظة جدًا
You either have to have a fair bit of money
يجب عليك إما أن تمتلك قسطًا من المال
and influence, or you have to devote your entire
والنفوذ، أو عليك تكريس جل حياتك
life to politics.
في الحياة السياسية
You have to become a party member
عليك أن تصبح عضوًا في حزب ما
and slowly start working up the ranks
وتعمل سعيًا للحصول على الترقية
until maybe, one day, you'll get to sit at a table
وربما يومًا ما تحظى بمقعد على طاولة
where a decision is being made.
حيث يصنع القرار
And last but not least,
أخيرًا وليس آخرًا
the language of the system —
لغة النظام
it's incredibly cryptic.
مشفرة بشكل معقد
It's done for lawyers, by lawyers,
فهي منجزة على أيدي محامين ومن أجلهم
and no one else can understand.
ولا أحد يمكن أن يفك طلاسمها
So, it's a system where we can
نستطيع من خلال هذا النظام
choose our authorities,
اختيار سلطاتنا
but we are completely left out on how those authorities
لكننا نجهل تمامًا كيف تصنع هذه السلطات
reach their decisions.
قراراتها
So, in a day where a new information technology
وحين تتوفر لدينا تكنولوجيا حديثة
allows us to participate globally in any conversation,
تتيح لنا المشاركة عالميًا في أي حوار
our barriers of information are completely lowered
فإن حواجز المعلومات تتضاءل
and we can, more than ever before,
وبوسعنا أكثر من أي وقت مضى
express our desires and our concerns.
أن نعتبر عن رغباتنا ومخاوفنا
Our political system remains the same
لم يتغير نظامنا السياسي
for the past 200 years
على مدار المئتي عام الماضية
and expects us to be contented with being simply passive recipients
ويتوقع منا أن نكتفي بالاستماع السلبي
of a monologue.
لمنولوجه الداخلي
So, it's really not surprising that
فليس من غير المتوقع إذًا
this kind of system is only able to produce
أن هذا النوع من الأنظمة لا ينتج سوى
two kinds of results:
نوعين من النتائج:
silence or noise.
الصمت أو الضجيج
Silence, in terms of citizens not engaging,
الصمت من خلال عدم إشراك المواطنين
simply not wanting to participate.
ببساطة لا توجد إرادة للمشاركة
There's this commonplace [idea] that I truly, truly dislike,
ثمة أمر شائع أمقته حقًا
and it's this idea that we citizens are naturally
وهو أننا بطبيعتنا كمواطنين
apathetic. That we shun commitment.
لا نبالي لدرجة أننا نتهرب من الالتزام
But, can you really blame us
لكن أيعقل إلقاء اللوم علينا
for not jumping at the opportunity of going
لعدم اتخاذ زمام المبادرة
to the middle of the city in the middle
والذهاب إلى وسط المدينة
of a working day to attend, physically,
أثناء ساعات العمل لحضور
a public hearing that has no impact
جلسة علنية ليس لها أي أثر
whatsoever?
على الإطلاق؟
Conflict is bound to happen between a system
الصراع هو النتيجة الحتمية بين نظام
that no longer represents, nor has any dialogue capacity,
لم يعد يمثل، أو لم يعد يتحمل أي حوار
and citizens that are increasingly used
والمواطنين الذين يتزايد لديهم
to representing themselves.
الشعور بالتعبير عن الذات
And, then we find noise:
من ثم هناك الضجيج:
Chile, Argentina, Brazil, Mexico Italy, France, Spain, the United States,
تشيلي، الأرجنتين، البرازيل، المكسيك إيطاليا، فرنسا، إسبانيا، الولايات المتحدة
they're all democracies.
جميعها بلدان ديمقراطية.
Their citizens have access to
حيث يسمح للمواطنين الولوج
the ballot boxes. But they still feel the need,
إلى صناديق الاقتراع، ولا زال لديهم الشعور
they need to take to the streets in order to be heard.
بالحاجة للنزول إلى الشارع لتصل آراؤهم
To me, it seems like the 18th-century
يبدو لي أن شعار القرن الثامن عشر
slogan that was the basis for the formation
المبني على تكوين
of our modern democracies, "No taxation
الديمقراطية الحديثة، "لا ضرائب
without representation,"
بدون تمثيل"
can now be updated to "No representation without a conversation."
يمكن تحديثه ليصبح "لا تمثيل دون حوار"
We want our seat at the table.
نريد مقعدنا على الطاولة
And rightly so.
وهذا حقنا
But in order to be part of this conversation,
لكن لنكون طرفًا في هذا الحوار
we need to know what we want to do next,
نحتاج لمعرفة الخطوة التالية
because political action is being able
فالعمل السياسي
to move from agitation
يتحرك الآن من الهياج
to construction.
إلى البناء
My generation has been incredibly good at
لقد أحسن الجيل الذي أنتمي إليه
using new networks and technologies
استخدام الشبكات والتقنيات الجديدة
to organize protests,
لتنظيم الاحتجاجات
protests that were able to successfully
التي تمكنت بنجاح
impose agendas,
من فرض أجندتها
roll back extremely pernicious legislation,
وإلغاء التشريعات السيئة
and even overthrow authoritarian governments.
وحتى الإطاحة بالحكومات الاستبدادية
And we should be immensely
ويجب أن نفتخر
proud of this.
بهذا الإنجاز
But, we also must admit that we
لكن علينا الاعتراف
haven't been good at using those
أننا لم نحسن استخدام
same networks and technologies
هذه الشبكات والتقنيات
to successfully articulate an alternative to what we're seeing
لنحدد بديلًا واضحًا لما نشهده الآن
and find the consensus and build the alliances that are needed
ونجد إجماعًا ونبني التحالفات الضرورية
to make it happen.
لتحقيق ذلك.
And so the risk that we face
والمخاطر التي نواجهها
is that we can create these huge power vacuums
هي أننا يمكن أن نحدث فراغًا كبيرًا في السلطة
that will very quickly get filled up by de facto
فراغًا ستملأه السلطات القوية
powers, like the military or highly
كالجيش أو
motivated and already organized groups
مجموعات متحفزة ومنظمة مسبقًا
that generally lie on the extremes.
والتي تقبع في الحدود القصوى
But our democracy is neither
لكن الديمقراطية ليست
just a matter of voting once every
مجرد التصويت مرة
couple of years.
كل بضعة سنوات
But it's not either the ability to bring millions onto the streets.
كما وليست القدرة على جر الملايين للطرقات
So the question I'd like to raise here,
والسؤال الذي يطرح نفسه هنا
and I do believe it's the most important question we need to answer,
وأعتقد أنه السؤال الأهم الذي يحتاج إلى إجابة
is this one:
السؤال هو:
If Internet is the new printing press,
إذا كان الإنترنت الصحافة المطبوعة الجديدة
then what is democracy for the Internet era?
فما هي الديمقراطية في عصر الإنترنت؟
What institutions do we want to build
ما هي المؤسسات التي نريد بناءها
for the 21st-century society?
لمجتمع القرن الواحد والعشرين
I don't have the answer, just in case.
لا أملك إجابة
I don't think anyone does.
ولا أعتقد أن لدى أحد إجابة
But I truly believe we can't afford to ignore this question anymore.
لكن لم يعد هناك مجال لتجاهل هذا السؤال
So, I'd like to share our experience
لذا أود أن أتشارك وإياكم تجربتنا
and what we've learned so far
وما تعلمناه حتى الآن
and hopefully contribute two cents
ونأمل أن نساهم بجزء بسيط
to this conversation.
في هذه المحادثة
Two years ago, with a group of friends from Argentina,
منذ سنتين بدأنا بالتعاون مع بعض الأصدقاء في الأرجنتين
we started thinking, "how can we get our representatives,
بالتفكير في طريقة لجعل ممثلينا
our elected representatives,
ممثلينا المنتخبين
to represent us?"
يمثلوننا حقًا؟
Marshall McLuhan once said that politics
ثمة مقولة للمارشال ماكلوهان
is solving today's problems with yesterday's tools.
أن السياسة تحل مشاكل اليوم بأدوات البارحة
So the question that motivated us was,
وكان السؤال الذي شكل الحافز لنا:
can we try and solve some of today's problems
هل بوسعنا حل بعض مشاكل اليوم
with the tools that we use every single day of our lives?
بأدوات نستخدمها كل يوم من حياتنا؟
Our first approach was to design and develop
في البداية قمنا بتصميم وتطوير
a piece of software called DemocracyOS.
تطبيق يدعى (ديموكراسي أو سي)
DemocracyOS is an open-source web application
(ديموكراسي أو سي) هو تطبيق متاح على الإنترنت
that is designed to become a bridge
تم تصميمه ليكون جسرًا
between citizens and their elected representatives
بين المواطنين وممثلهم المنتخب
to make it easier for us to participate from our everyday lives.
لتسهيل مشاركتنا بشكل يومي
So first of all, you can get informed so every new
أولًا يمكنك الحصول على المعلومات متجددة
project that gets introduced in Congress
عن أي مشروع جديد تم تقديمه للكونغرس
gets immediately translated and explained
مع ترجمة فورية وشرح
in plain language on this platform.
بلغة مبسطة على هذا البرنامج
But we all know that social change
لكننا نعلم أن التغيير الاجتماعي
is not going to come from just knowing
لن يأتي من مجرد معرفة
more information,
المزيد من المعلومات
but from doing something with it.
بل من القيام بشيء آخر أيضًا
So better access to information
إذا تسهيل الوصول إلى المعلومات
should lead to a conversation
لا بد أن يقود إلى محادثة
about what we're going to do next,
عما يجب أن نفعله بعد ذلك
and DemocracyOS allows for that.
و(ديموكراسي أو سي) يتيح ذلك
Because we believe that democracy is
لأننا نعتقد أن الديمقراطية
not just a matter of stacking up
ليست مجرد تكديس
preferences, one on top of each other,
للامتيازات فوق بعضها البعض
but that our healthy and robust public debate
وإنما يجب أن يكون الحوار الصحي والسليم
should be, once again, one of its fundamental values.
مرة أخرى أحد القيم الأساسية لها
So DemocracyOS is about persuading and being persuaded.
يتركز تطبيق (ديموكراسي أو سي) حول الإقناع والاقتناع
It's about reaching a consensus
يهدف للوصول إلى الإجماع
as much as finding a proper way
بقدر ما نجد طريقة مناسبة
of channeling our disagreement.
لنعبر عن اختلافنا بالرأي
And finally, you can vote
وأخيرًا يمكنك التصويت
how you would like your elected representative to vote.
كيف تود أن يقوم ناخبك بالتصويت
And if you do not feel comfortable
وإذا كنت غير مرتاح
voting on a certain issue,
للتصويت على مسألة ما
you can always delegate your vote
يمكنك دائمًا تفويض صوتك
to someone else, allowing
لشخص ما مما يسمح
for a dynamic and emerging social leadership.
بقيادة اجتماعية ديناميكية
It suddenly became very easy for us
يصبح الأمر غاية في السهولة
to simply compare these results
للمقارنة بين هذه النتائج
with how our representatives were
وكيف يقوم ممثلونا
voting in Congress.
بالتصويت في الكونغرس
But, it also became very evident that
لكن يبدو واضحًا
technology was not going to do the trick.
أن التكنولوجيا لن تفي بالغرض
What we needed to do to was to find
ما كنا نريد فعله هو إيجاد
actors that were able to
ممثلين قادرين
grab this distributed knowledge
على انتزاع المعلومات الموزعة
in society and use it to make better and more fair decisions.
في المجتمع واستخدامها للخروج بقرارات أفضل وأكثر إنصافًا
So we reached out to traditional political parties
وتواصلنا مع أحزابنا السياسية التقليدية
and we offered them DemocracyOS.
وعرضنا عليهم تطبيق (ديموكراسي أو سي)
We said, "Look, here you have a platform that you can use to build
قلنا لهم: "لديكم هنا منبر يمكنكم استخدامه لبناء
a two-way conversation with your constituencies."
محادثة ثنائية مع الناخبين"
And yes, we failed.
وقد فشلنا
We failed big time.
فشلنا فشلًا ذريعًا
We were sent to play outside like little kids.
أرسلونا لنلعب في الخارج كأطفال صغار
Amongst other things, we were called naive.
علاوة على وصفنا بالسذّج.
And I must be honest: I think, in hindsight, we were.
وبصراحة أدركنا ذلك متأخرين
Because the challenges that we face, they're not
لأن التحديات التي تعترضنا لا علاقة لها
technological, they're cultural.
بالتكنولوجيا، بل بالثقافة
Political parties were never willing
لم تكن الأحزاب السياسية راغبة
to change the way they make their decisions.
بتغيير طريقة صنع قراراتها
So it suddenly became a bit obvious
وقد بدا واضحًا
that if we wanted to move forward with this idea,
أننا إذا أردنا المضي قدمًا بهذه الفكرة
we needed to do it ourselves.
فيجب أن نعتمد على أنفسنا
And so we took quite a leap of faith,
وبهذا قفزنا في المجهول
and in August last year, we founded
وفي أغسطس الفائت أسسنا
our own political party,
حزبنا السياسي
El Partido de la Red,
(إل بارتيدو دي لا ريد)
or the Net Party, in the city of Buenos Aires.
أو "حزب الإنترنت"، في مدينة بوينس أيرس
And taking an even bigger leap of faith,
وبعد قفزة أكبر في المجهول
we ran for elections in October last year
دخلنا الانتخابات في أكتوبر الفائت
with this idea:
بهذه الفكرة:
if we want a seat in Congress,
إذا أردنا مقعدًا في الكونغرس
our candidate, our representatives
فإن مرشحنا وممثلينا
were always going to vote according to
كانوا يصوتون دائمًا وفقًا
what citizens decided on DemocracyOS.
لقرار المواطنين عبر (ديموكراسي أو إس)
Every single project that got introduced
كل مشروع يتم طرحه
in Congress, we were going vote
في الكوغرس، كنا نقوم بالتصويت
according to what citizens decided on an online platform.
بناء على قرار المواطنين عبر المنبر الإلكتروني
It was our way of hacking the political system.
إنها طريقتنا في اختراق النظام السياسي
We understood that if we wanted
فهمنا أن الطريقة الوحيدة
to become part of the conversation,
لنكون جزء من المحادثة
to have a seat at the table,
ولحجز مقعد على الطاولة
we needed to become valid stakeholders,
هي بأن نصبح حملة أسهم
and the only way of doing it is to play by the system rules.
ولا يمكن القيام بذلك إلا باللعب وفقًا لقوانين النظام
But we were hacking it in the sense that
لكننا اخترقناه بهدف إحداث تغيير
we were radically changing the way a political party
بالطريقة التي يتبعها الأحزاب السياسية
makes its decisions.
في صنع القرارا
For the first time, we were making our decisions
للمرة الأولى، كنا نصنع القرارات
together with those who we were
بالتعاون مع هؤلاء الذين كانوا
affecting directly by those decisions.
يتأثرون مباشرة بهذه القرارات
It was a very, very bold move for a two-month-old party
كانت خطوة جريئة جدًا بالنسبة لحزب عمره شهران
in the city of Buenos Aires.
في مدينة بوينس أيريس
But it got attention.
لكن ذلك استدعى الانتباه
We got 22,000 votes, that's 1.2 percent of the votes,
كسبنا 22,000 صوت، أي 1.2 بالمئة من الأصوات
and we came in second for the local options.
وحللنا بالمرتبة الثانية في الخيارات المحلية
So, even if that wasn't enough to win a
حتى وإن كان هذا غير كافٍ للفوز
seat in Congress, it was enough
بمقعد في الكونغرس، لكنه كان كافيًا
for us to become part of the conversation,
بالنسبة لنا أن نكون جزء من الحوار
to the extent that next month,
لدرجة أنه في الشهر القادم
Congress, as an institution, is launching
سيطلق الكونغرس، كمؤسسة
for the first time in Argentina's history,
للمرة الأولى في تاريخ الأرجنتين
a DemocracyOS to discuss,
تطبيق (ديموكراسي أو سي)
with the citizens, three pieces of legislation:
لمناقشة المواطنين في ثلاثة تشريعات:
two on urban transportation and
اثنين عن وسائل النقل
one on the use of public space.
وواحد عن استخدام المرافق العامة
Of course, our elected representatives are not
بالطبع لا يقول ممثلينا المنتخبين
saying, "Yes, we're going to vote
"أجل سنقوم بالتصويت
according to what citizens decide,"
وفقًا لقرار المواطنين"
but they're willing to try.
لكنهم راغبون بالمحاولة
They're willing to open up a new space
لديهم رغبة في فتح مساحة جديدة
for citizen engagement and hopefully
لمشاركة المواطنين على أمل
they'll be willing to listen as well.
أن تكون لديهم الرغبة بالإنصات أيضًا
Our political system can be transformed,
يمكن تغيير نظامنا السياسي
and not by subverting it, by destroying it,
ليس بتدميره وتخريبه
but by rewiring it with the tools that
بل بتجهيزه بالأدوات
Internet affords us now.
التي يؤمنها الإنترنت اليوم
But a real challenge is to find, to design
لكن التحدي الحقيقي إيجاد وتصميم
to create, to empower those connectors
وإحداث وتعزيز دور وسائل التواصل هذه
that are able to innovate, to transform
التي تقود للابتكار والتجديد
noise and silence into signal
وتحويل الضجة والصمت إلى إشارة
and finally bring our democracies
وأخيرًا لإيصال الديمقراطية
to the 21st century.
إلى القرن الواحد والعشرين
I'm not saying it's easy.
لا أدعي أن الأمر سهل
But in our experience, we actually stand a chance
لكن من خلال تجربتنا، تلمسنا إمكانية
of making it work.
إنجاح هذا المشروع
And in my heart, it's most definitely
وأؤمن أن الأمر
worth trying.
يستحق المحاولة
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)